Okay, so let's discuss the RACI chart now,
or the RAC chart, as
it's sometimes called.
Now, I'm sure many of you have come across
an RACI chart before, right, at least some
variation of one is very commonly used,
but of course, some of you may not have
come across an RACI chart or a RAC chart
before.
So I'm just going to
go through just some of
the very basics that you
need for the PMP exam.
Now, whenever anybody is performing any
work on a project, right, the performing,
a task, they need to have some
accountability, right?
There needs to be, you know, some
knowledge of team members need to know who
is working on a particular task, right, or
who is accountable for a particular task.
That all needs to be documented,
right?
Because, you know, if there is a problem,
then, you know, we can identify very
simply who or very quickly, we can
identify, all right, who worked on this
task and or who is accountable for this
task or, you know, who's responsible for
performing this task and so and so and so
forth.
And that really is what the RACI chart of
the RAC chart is capturing.
Now, what RAC stands for is responsible,
accountable, consult and inform.
Right.
So R is obviously responsible.
A is accountable, C is consult and I is
informed.
And essentially what you're doing is
across the top here, you are listing out
all of your different roles on your
project.
And this is obviously a very simple little
example here.
Right, you list out all of the different
roles on the project.
We've got the PMO who would be a key
stakeholder.
We've got the project manager,
business analyst, solution architect,
developers, right?
These are all, say, the different roles on
your project.
And then down the side here on the left
and side, you're going to list out all of
your different activities, right, activity
one or task one, task two, task three.
I mean, whatever they are.
Right.
So there could be individual activities,
right, down to the granular level.
or they could be the work package level,
right?
So these could be work packages or they
could be activities.
And then for each item, each activity,
in this case, each task, you're going to
list out who is responsible for performing
the work, who is accountable for the work,
right?
Who needs to be consulted and who needs to
be informed?
All right.
So what does that mean?
All right, so let's talk about
responsible.
Responsible is basically the person who is
going to be performing the work.
Responsible means that they are
responsible.
They are basically going to be performing
the actual work.
That is what responsible means.
Whereas accountable
is basically, who has to
explain to senior
management what went wrong?
Just as a nutshell, that's kind of what it
means in reality.
That's what it ends up meaning.
So as a very, very simple example,
right?
You have a junior analyst that's going to
be responsible for performing the work.
But the team lead is going to be
accountable.
If that junior analyst messes up, the
team lead has to explain what went wrong.
It's just like when, you know,
you're doing some work, your manager
delegates work to you, you are responsible
for performing the work, right?
But it's your manager who is accountable
for the work that you do.
If you mess up, it's a manager that has to
explain to senior management, you know,
what went wrong?
So that's the difference between
responsible and accountable.
Consult means we need input from this
person.
So this person is either a subject matter
expert or this person is a decision maker,
right?
You know, this person is knowledgeable.
We need to say invite this person to a
meeting.
So we need input from this person.
And that I means inform.
this person needs to be communicated to.
They need to be informed.
So either before the task is performed or
during or while the task is in progress or
after the task is complete, they need to
be informed in some way.
So in this very simple example here,
right, and again, very, very high level
example, right, we can see here then that
for task three, right, or let's just look
at task four here, solution architect is
responsible for performing task four,
whereas the project manager here is
accountable.
So the project manager is accountable.
Project manager has to
explain what went wrong
if the solution architect made a mistake.
The PMO needs to be consulted,
right?
If there's any changes to task for or we
need to make any updates or of any kind,
right, we need to consult with the PMO,
right?
And then the business analysts and
developers need to be informed.
Just as a very simple example,
right?
There's just a very, very, obviously,
a very high level simple example.
Now, basic rules, basic rules regarding
the RACI chart.
First of all, every activity needs to have
at least one person responsible.
You may have more than one.
Now here, only one activity is showing an
R, but only one person can be responsible.
The person responsible can also be the
person accountable.
So you can have two, as in task one, the
project manager is
accountable and responsible.
right but every activity needs to have at
least one person responsible you may have
more than one person responsible i mean
essentially if you don't have somebody
responsible who's going to do the work
it's not going to get done but every
activity needs to have only one a only one
person can be accountable and that's a
basic rule not every activity needs to
have a c a consult not every activity
needs to have an i and inform i mean they
can do but that's not necessary and you
know This example, the showing every
activity with a C and an I, but not
necessarily every activity needs to have a
C and a I.
But every activity needs to have at least
one R and only one A.
And that's the basic principle behind the
RACI chart.